American Council of Learned Societies. Committee on Native American Languages. 1882-1958 Mss.497.3.B63c
American Philosophical Society
- Wishram
  - Wishram directional elements, 1930; AMs, 1L.; Dyk, Walter, 1899-1972
    Freeman and Smith 3906
    Cf. Dyk and Hymes (1956).
  - Wishram grammatical notes, 1931; AMs, 45 slips.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Lecture notes taken by Morris Swadesh, Sapir's field work in 1905. Waiter Dyk used Sapir's Wishram materials.
    Freeman and Smith 3907
    Cf. note in Dyk and Hymes (1956): 238.
  - Wishram in early days, n.d.; TMs and AMs, ca.50L.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Ethnographic notes in English with some vocabulary items. Five pages of place-names possibly by J. Wolf.
    Freeman and Smith 4906
  - Wasco-Wishram Chinook linguistic material, 1905, 1930-1933, 1951, 1954; Cy and microfilm of AMs, ca. 22, 000 slips and 5 reels.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939, Walter Dyk, and Dell H. Hymes, comps.
    Freeman and Smith 4907
- Xinca
  - Zoque and Xinca compared with Penutian, 1924; TMs and AMs, 4L.; Dixon, Roland Burrage, 1875-1934
    In EnglishZoque-Penutian and English-Xinca-Penutian. Typed tabular lists of 60 and 45 items. Penutian languages identified by abbreviation. Handwritten additions by Edward Sapir.
    Freeman and Smith 3909
- Yakima
  - Pandosy's Yakama grammar, AMs, 5L.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Based on Pandosy (1862): 12-16 and 3859. Contains "substantives, adjectives, lexical similarities between Chinookan and Sahaptin." Alphabetical list by English meaning. Comparison is Sapir's.
    Freeman and Smith 3910
- Yana
  - Yana and Navaho notes from Edward Sapir, 1932; AMs, 1 notebook (ca.180p.); Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Class notes from Sapir lectures on Yana, Navaho, with comparative Athapascan material.
    Freeman and Smith 3915
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, grantee, 1950.
  - Yana vocabulary, 1907-1925; TMs and AMs, card and slip file, 240L. and 4, 500 cards and slips.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Duplicate of Yana dictionary material, No. 3911, used in No. 3914. Consists of "first position elements" for North Yana; also Central and some Yahi materials, alphabetically arranged. Letter of Sapir to A. L. Kroeber, Aug. 21, 1925.
    Freeman and Smith 3913
    Donor, Alfred L. Kroeber, grantee, 1952
  - Yana dictionary, 1953; TMs with MS. additions and corrections, 212L.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939, and Morris Swadesh
    In Yana-English. Dictionary arranged phonetically by Yana. Introduction by Morris Swadesh, who prepared the dictionary from Sapir materials. Carbon of earlier introduction (Oct. 1952) and Verifax copy of introduction to Yana Dictionary ... ed. Mary R. Haas.
    Freeman and Smith 3914
    Published with additions and English-Yana sections as Haas (1960).
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, grantee, 1953
  - Yana notebooks, ca. 1907-1928; AMs, 25 notebooks.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Material copied from No. 3913. Contains vocabulary and grammar in form of lists. Material utilized by Morris Swadesh in preparing Yana dictionary No. 3914. Vocabulary arranged by initial sound; suffixes ordered alphabetically by Yana; phonetics, verbs, nouns, pronouns, adverbs.
    Freeman and Smith 3911
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 39-40
  - Yana notes, 1907-1925; AMs, 96 slips.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    A lexical file.
    Freeman and Smith 3912
- Yuchi
  - English-Yuchi dictionary, n.d.; T. and AMs, 109p..; Wagner, Gunter, comp.
    Includes: English-Yuchi dictionary; introduc tory and explanatory section; reference to a Yuchi-English section which is wanting.
    Freeman and Smith 4925
- Yuki
  - Preliminary report on Yuki tones; Atlantic City, Dec. 31, 1932; TMs, 8p.; Uldall, Hans J.
    Discussion of syllable structure, stems, and suffixes and of the behavior of tones with stems and suffixes; list of stem forms.
    Freeman and Smith 4926
- Yuman
  - Vocabulary in five Yuman languages, 1917; TMs, 1L.; Gifford, Edward W.
    35 English words, including numerals, with equivalents in Cocopa, Southern Diegueno, Northern Diegueno, Kamia, and Yuma. Informants identified at head of each column. Southern and Lower California.
    Freeman and Smith 3926
- Yurok
  - Short vocabulary in Yurok, n.d.; AMs Cy, 30p.; Angulo, Jaime de and Lucy S. Freeland
    English-Yurok vocabulary with phonetic keys. Informant: Robert Nat, Lower Klamath River.
    Freeman and Smith 4928
  - Yurok field notes, 1927; AMs, 1 notebook (91p.); Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Contains word lists, paradigms, texts from Hupa (?) Reservation.
    Freeman and Smith 3928
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 35
- Zapotec
  - Estudio gramatical de las lenguas de la familia zapoteca, 1923; AMs Cy, 529L., illus.; Angulo, Jaime de
    Study based on field work in 1922, in which the author proposes divisions of the Zapotec family into Zapotec, Mixtec, Chatino, Amuzgo, Trique, Cuicatec, Mazatec, and Chocho. Makes dialectical comparison of phonological and morphological features. Includes comparative word list, semantically arranged. Images include ten ink sketches of maps showing linguistic groups., in part 1 of 3.
    Freeman and Smith 3941
  - Zapotec text in the Miahuatec dialect, n.d.; AMs, 34p.; Angulo, Jaime de
    Text with Spanish and English translations.
    Freeman and Smith 4929
  - MetodologC-a linguC-stica, II, ca. 1925; AMs Cy, 28L.; Angulo, Jaime de
    In Spanish. Discussion of Zapotec materials, the argument following Sapir (1921b). Cf. similar point of view in de Angulo and Freeland (1935).
    Freeman and Smith 3942
  - Zapotecan texts, 1922?-1930; TMs, 74L.; Angulo, Jaime de
    Texts with interlinear and some free transIztion of Chinanteco, Mazateco, Cuicateco, Mixteco, Chatino, and mountain and valley dialects of Zapotec. Tones are indicated. Includes sentences from everyday speech and folkloristic texts.
    Freeman and Smith 3943
  - Zapotec texts and word list, n.d., ca.1920; TMs and AMs, 7L.; Unidentified
    In Zapotec-Spanish. Text with interlinear translation. Printed Spanish vocabulary list with typed Zapotecan entries.
    Freeman and Smith 3978
  - Vocabularies in various Zapotec dialects, 1941; TMs Cy and AMs, 120L.; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    In Spanish-Zapotec. 10 vocabulary lists of from 17 to 742 items, taken from informants at various villages; 4 Ixtlan, 5 Villa Alta lists, and I Tehuantepec list.
    Freeman and Smith 3976
  - Zapotec notes, 1941; TMs and AMs, 144L.; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    In Spanish. Relates to Tehuantepec, Ixtlan, and Villa Alta dialects. Covers tonal contours; presents paradigms. Miscellaneous brief texts, material on tones. 2 copies, El Alfabeto Zapoteco, and also, Conclusiones Provisionales sobre el Sistema FonC3mico del Zapoteca. Includes 2 letters of Otis and Mary Leal to Swadesh, Dec. 4, 1940 and July 23, 1947, relating to field work and Zapotec tones.
    Freeman and Smith 3977
  - El idioma de los Zapotecos, 1940; TMs Cy, 43L.; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    In Spanish. A general descriptive and comparative treatment, with special reference to Ixtl n, Yatzachi, and Tehuantepec dialects. Reconstructs proto-Zapotec. Some MS. revisions made in 1946.
    Freeman and Smith 3975
- Zuni
  - Zuni word list, 1920; AMs, 1 notebook.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Word lists and shorthand ethnographic notes, subsequently transcribed elsewhere.
    Freeman and Smith 3993
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 54
  - Zuni lexicon, n.d.; AMs, ca. 7,000 slips.; Bunzel, Ruth Leah, 1898-
    Arranged alphabetically and also by grammatical categories. Based, apparently, on field notes.
    Freeman and Smith 3994